James C. Luitweiler Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
James C. Luitweiler Papers.
undated, 1903-1982.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Luitweiler, James C.
2 linear feet.
James Luitweiler (1890-1982) was born and raised in York, Pennsylvania and the Yucatan peninsula (Mexico, 1906-1911). An international lawyer and businessman, Luitweiler served as Secretary to the American Land Commission Canal Zone in 1913.
MSS19920048
Biography
James Luitweiler (1890-1982) was born and raised in York, Pennsylvania and the Yucatan peninsula (Mexico, 1906-1911). An international lawyer and businessman, Luitweiler served as Secretary to the American Land Commission Canal Zone in 1913. He received his law degree from the University of Pennsylvania in 1915 and served with the American Legation to Buenos Aires and Santiago from 1915 until 1917. Subsequent to these activities he returned to New York and established himself in the field of international finance.
Scope and Content
The collection includes correspondence to and from Luitweiler, typescripts and reports concerning the activities of the Legation in South America and National City Bank of New York, materials concerning the retention of the Panama Canal and a collection of personal photographs taken during his travels in Mexico and Central and South America, chiefly before 1920.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence ( 1906-1981 ) has been subdivided into two subseries: Personal and Political.
Series II: Writings ( undated, 1909-1980 ) includes essays and written works, published and unpublished.
Series III: Subject Files ( 1903-1982 ) includes and alphabetical file of information, primarily concerning Panama.
Series IV: Photographs ( 1908-1978 ) includes photos taken by Luitweiler.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Latin America. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Manuscripts.; Notes.; Obituaries.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased in 1992.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Correspondence, 1906-1981
  - Personal
    - Parents (of James Luitweiler), 1906 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - 1907 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - 1907 April - June (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - 1907 August - December (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - 1908 January - December (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - 1909 January - December (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - Notebook to Sister, 1910 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - 1910 January - July (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - 1910 August - December (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - 1911 January - December (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - 1912 January - December (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - 1913 January - May (Box 2:, Folder 12)
    - 1913 June - December (Box 2:, Folder 13)
    - 1914 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 14)
    - 1915-1916 (Box 2:, Folder 15)
    - 1917 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 16)
    - 1918 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 17)
    - 1938 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 18)
    - Handwriting analysis, 1939 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
    - 1940-1943 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
    - Luitweiler, James and Preston, 1941-1942 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
  - Political
    - 1916-1917 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
    - 1967-1978 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
    - Panama Treaty, 1977-1978 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
    - Helms, Jesse (Senator), 1977-1981 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
- Series II: Writings, undated, 1909-1980
  - Early Essays, undated (Box 3:, Folder 27)
  - Diary (fishing with Zane Grey), 1909 (Box 3:, Folder 28)
  - Machu Picchu, 1915 (Box 3:, Folder 29)
  - South American reports, 1916 (Box 3:, Folder 30)
  - Yucatan, 1967 (Box 3:, Folder 31)
  - Essays
    - Political, 1958-1980 (Box 3:, Folder 32)
    - Blind Mrs. Davies, undated (Box 3:, Folder 33)
    - An Austrian Baron of the Old School, 1967 (Box 3:, Folder 34)
    - Family, undated (Box 3:, Folder 35)
    - Law School, 1967 (Box 3:, Folder 36)
    - Labor Day/Duel with a Pisote, 1968 (Box 3:, Folder 37)
    - Mores in Scandinavia, 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 38)
    - Russian Women, undated (Box 3:, Folder 39)
    - Late Essays, undated (Box 3:, Folder 40)
    - A Layman watches a surgeon at work, undated (Box 3:, Folder 41)
  - Published
    - Carnegie report on Bolivia, 1915 (Box 3:, Folder 42)
    - City Bank of New York S. American work, 1916 (Box 3:, Folder 43)
    - Report on loans, 1930 (Box 3:, Folder 44)
    - Tryon Daily Bulletin, 1978-1980 (Box 3:, Folder 45)
    - Reports on Canal Treaty, 1977-1980 (Box 3:, Folder 46)
- Series III: Subject Files, 1903-1982
  - Pan-American Union—L.S. Row and address on Mexico, 1916-1917 (Box 4:, Folder 47)
  - Panama Canal, 1903-1974 (Box 4:, Folder 48)
  - Panama Canal, 1976-1977 (Box 4:, Folder 49)
  - Panama Canal, 1978-1981 (Box 4:, Folder 50)
  - Speeches, 1977-1978 (Box 4:, Folder 51)
  - Obituary, 1982 (Box 4:, Folder 52)
- Series IV: Photographs, undated, 1908-1978
  - Luitweiler, 1978 (Box 4:, Folder 53)
  - Lima, Rio, Curzo, undated (Box 4:, Folder 54)
  - Bolivia, Iguaza and unidentified, undated (Box 4:, Folder 55)
  - Yucatan and Bolivia, 1908 (Box 4:, Folder 56)